<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/home/lou/Public/TEI/TEICSS/tei.css" type="text/css"
 ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:t="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2015-08"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the TEI Technical Council</title><meeting n="2015-08" when="2015-08-31">TEI Technical Council online
     meeting : <date>31 August 2015</date></meeting></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>TEI Website</distributor><idno>TCM072</idno></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Retagged from a WordPress HTML file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2023-04-27">Archival header confected</change><change>Extracted from Word Press article with id post-21928</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div>
		
		<!-- <div class="teiheader"><filedesc><titlestmt><title></title><author>TEI Technical Council</author></titlestmt><editionstmt><edition><date>2015-09-18</date></edition></editionstmt><publicationstmt>
<p>unknown</p>
</publicationstmt><sourcedesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p>
<p>      </sourcedesc></filedesc><encodingdesc><appinfo><application id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label>
        </application></appinfo></encodingdesc><revisiondesc><listchange><change><date>2015-09-18T15:41:48Z</date><name/></change></listchange></revisiondesc></div> -->
<p>Teleconference 2015-08-31 14:00 UTC</p>
	 <p>Present</p><list style="ul">
<item>Hugh Cayless (HC)</item>
<item>Syd Bauman (SB)</item>
<item>Peter Stadler (PWS)</item>
<item>James Cummings (JC)</item>
<item>Martin Holmes (MH)</item>
<item>Lou Burnard (LB)</item>
</list>
	 <p>Apologies</p>
<list style="ul">
<item>Stefanie Gehrke (SG)</item>
<item>Raff Viglianti (RV)</item>
</list>
<p>started 14:06; ended 15:51</p>
<div><head>Agenda
        </head><list style="ul">
<item>Conference and F2F<list style="ul">
<item>Sunday meeting is booked in same
                place as business meeting in the Mama Shelter Hotel</item>
<item>The meeting will be
                there all day Sunday 25 October, then use the workshop venue room for Monday 26
                October and first half of Tuesday 27 October</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Migration Status and Issues<list style="ul">
<item>Remember, there is a pointer
                to the Sourceforge repository and a TEI web page with instructions for using it on
                the Guidelines’ index page (<ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/766/"><hi style="underline color(1155CC)">Bug #766</hi></ref>) There is also other
                documentation here and there which points specifically to SF. And legacy URLs which
                point there from many systems. We’ll have to track those down.</item>
<item>JC and MH
                would be reluctant to move if SF were more trustworthy. LB confirms that using
                Subversion on GitHub “nearly works”. HC worries about branching. All agree that if
                we’re moving to GitHub, we should move to git too. Those skilled with git should
                help those who are new to it. Practice is required. MH suggests that the repo should
                be called “P5” instead of “Guidelines”. PWS asks whether we’ve moved yet or not. HC:
                The “Guidelines” (=P5) one can, if we agree, be the repo going forward. We should
                use Guidelines-Test for playing around and migrating tickets. JC points out that
                Guidelines = TEI as it has more than P5 in it. (Action on JC: Rename Guidelines
                Repository on TEIC github organisation. DONE). Should we move now or wait until
                after a release? Some disagreement. LB and SB feel it’s vital to keep the rhythm of
                the releases going, and put off the migration; others fear that SF is now so
                unreliable that it’s justifiable to defer a release. Consensus seems to be to move
                to GitHub, and try to release from there, with a backup plan to push from
                GitHub/master to SF, and build from there. I.e., HC &amp; MH will work on release
                process from GitHub for 2 weeks, and then decide which we do.</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Pure ODD and DTDs<list style="ul">
<item>Problem is that in <hi style="italic">impureODD</hi> there are some redundant &lt;rng:group&gt; elements inserted by
                the wise men of long ago to ensure that DTD generation worked correctly (i.e. had
                parens in right places). &lt;rng:group&gt; is mostly correctly translated as
                <gi>sequence</gi> in pure odd. But we have a schematron rule which prohibits
                <gi>sequence</gi>s of only one thing. </item>
<item>Simply wrapping all %model.xxx; in
                parens won’t work: it generates error for mixed content models</item>
<item>Trying to
                figure out what’s going on in odd2dtd.xsl is Hard. Very Hard. You may think
                diamonds, granite, or tungsten are pretty hard. They are like yoghurt in comparison
                to this.</item>
<item>Cunning plan — post-tweak the p5subset.xml file to add spurious
                <gi>sequence</gi> elements looks promising. LB has so far identified 92 cases which
                need tweaking. SB volunteers to write the hack itself.</item>
</list>
</item>
<item><gi>xenoData</gi> (SB):<list style="ul">
<item>categorization: <gi>xenoData</gi>
                currently has a derived @type with values “source” and “transcription”; this is
                wrong, as <gi>xenoData</gi> is repeatable and categorizable, so @type is needed for
                categorization; i.e., @type is where “this is hand-generated METS information” or
                “this Dublin Core generated by program X” should go. But where then does “source” vs
                “thisTEI” go? SB would prefer to create a new @about, @describes, or @scope for
                “source” vs “thisTEI”.<lb/>General consensus in favour of @scope with suggested
                values of source/transcription/other?. Would also be a member of att.typed to give
                users the option to categorize as they need to.</item>
<item>since we’re letting
                non-XML data in, is an @encoding or similar necessary? (SB wonders if permitting
                &lt;tei:binaryObject&gt; as a child of <gi>xenoData</gi> would do the trick?)
                Consensus is that @encoding is not needed, at least initially.</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Abstract Model enforcement with Schematron<list style="ul">
<item><ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/commit/fc6d0e79f12e90b09c37c89200f36d453e27c10c"><hi style="underline color(1155CC)">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/commit/fc6d0e79f12e90b09c37c89200f36d453e27c10c</hi></ref></item>
<item>Basic point is global checking that, e.g., nowhere is there a div inside
                a p, and other similar things which should be true. Will support the proposed
                changes to the appcrit model that JC still worries about, this will stop people
                doing stupid stuff, hopefully, for those using schematron only</item>
<item>Need to
                worry about what <gi>p</gi>-inside-<gi>p</gi> situations are, in fact, aligned with
                abstract model (e.g., p/note/p). HC will continue implementing, but will talk to SB
                about how more automated Schematron generation based on the class system might be
                achieved. JC thinks there must be a better way we can generate this even if it
                involves revision of the class system. (He suggests pure ODD localisation of content
                models but SB says this won’t help.)</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Updates needed to language identification (SB)<list style="ul">
<item>SB
                informs Council the language identification parts of Guidelines need some updating —
                volunteers to do the work himself, but needs guidance on where (Sourceforge vs
                GitHub) and (if using `git`) how to create ticket, make changes, and test
                them.</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>TEI Simple (JC)<list style="ul">
<item>JC informs Council that the TEI Simple
                project is working hard. He has made available draft Spec files for inclusion in the
                Guidelines for the Processing Model at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/tree/master/guidelines-specs"><hi style="underline color(1155CC)">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple/tree/master/guidelines-specs</hi></ref> and
                is drafting prose to go with these for the TD chapter. It would be nice to get this in
                the next release. The TEI Simple customization can be added to a later release if
                not ready. JC is now working on the “Performance Indicators” which is a
                <gi>taxonomy</gi> with set of nested categories indicating what kinds of markup you
                can expect a text to have. (e.g. are there names, do they have @ref, etc.)
              </item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Next Release? Who? When? Where? What? Why?<list style="ul">
<item>Who = a panel
                of experts</item>
<item>When = early–mid October; 1 October Freeze</item>
<item>Where
                = internet</item>
<item>What = include <gi>xenoData</gi>, pureODD improvements, maybe
                <gi>p</gi>-inside-<gi>rdg</gi>, etc.</item>
<item>Why = it’s our
                job</item>
<item>Release 2.9.0 Codename: <hi style="bold color(0B5394)">Stormageddon</hi></item>
</list>
</item>
</list>
</div>
	</div></body><!-- #post-## --></text></TEI>