<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="teixlite.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
"http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>]
>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Charge for the TEI Council's Manuscript Description Taskforce</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>TEI</distributor>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Loosely based on AI1P01</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>2 Feb 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Lou</name>
<resp>Draft</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>First draft</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
/<body>
<div><head>Background</head>

<p>Over the last few years, several groups have worked
on the problem of defining standards for manuscript description.
Of particular relevance to the TEI are :
<list>
<item>	The TEI Medieval Manuscripts Description Work Group (TEI 
MMSS), headed by Consuelo Dutschke and Ambrogio Piazzoni, which first 
met in 1998; the last meeting (for which there are minutes) was in the autumn 
of 2000. Its proposed DTD is available on the <xref url="http://www.stg.brown.edu/~tei-mmss/">TEI-MMSS website</xref>, but the final report of the Work 
Group, including the documentation for the DTD, has not yet been made 
available.</item>
<item>	MASTER (Manuscript Access through Standards for Electronic 
Records), an EU-funded project headed by Peter Robinson, which ran from 
January 1999 to June 2001. The reference manual for the MASTER DTD, and 
the DTD itself, both unrevised since the end of the project period, are 
available at <xref url="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Master/Reference/">the
	Master project website</xref>.
      </item>
     </list></p>
<p>There is, despite an avowed intention that there should not be, a degree of 
discrepancy between the two DTDs.  In the absence of documentation from 
the Work Group, it is hard to assess the extent or rationale for the
     discrepancy,
although in most cases it will presumably have been 
that one of the groups has simply paid more attention to one area than the 
other did.  The MASTER project, for example, never finalised its discussion 
on seals, while the Work Group did, whereas MASTER developed quite 
sophisticated mechanisms for dealing with personal and place names, an area 
untouched by the Work Group.  In this sense, the two schemes may be said to 
complement each other. There appears, however, to be one fundamental 
difference between to two, which is a tendency on the part of the Work Group 
toward a looser structure, but it is unlikely that the differences between the 
two are so great in this regard that a reconciliation is impossible.  
    </p><p>
At its 2001 meeting, the TEI Council requested the two groups to work
towards a consensus, or to produce reports which could be collated by a
third party, but no progress has yet been reported. The Council has now
determined that a small task force should be charged with the job of
identifying a common set of proposals, which will review both sets of
proposals as currently articulated, also taking into account
complementary work done in this area by other agencies, notably the
Reportorium of Old Bulgarian Literarture and Letters.
    </p>
   </div>
<div><head>Work Plan</head>
<p>The Task force is requested:-
<list>
<item> to review the current state of TEI-based recommendations for the
detailed description of manuscript materials, in particular the
proposals from Master, the TEI Workgroup, and the ROBLL</item>

<item> to identify and define a common subset of those recommendations
adequate to the needs of the TEI community</item>

<item>to document that set of recommendations in such a way as to facilitate
their inclusion in TEI P5, once approved by the TEI Council</item>
     </list>
    </p>
<p>The task force should do its work by email, mailing list, or telephone
as the head of the group sees fit. No funding is available for in-person
meetings.
    </p>


   </div>
<div><head>Timetable</head>

<p>A preliminary report should be submitted by the Chair in advance of the
meeting of the May 2003 meeting of the Council. A final report should be
available by 1st October 2003.
    </p>
   </div>
<div><head>Membership</head>

<p>The Chair of the group is Matthew Driscoll. Members proposed by the
     Council are Merillee Proffitt and David Birnbaum. The Chair may
     choose to co-opt help from outside sources at his discretion. The
     TEI editors are ex officio members of the Taskforce.
    </p>

   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>



