<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="teixlite.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
"http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd" [
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>]
>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Charge for the TEI Council's Metalanguage Taskforce</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>TEI</distributor>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Loosely based on AI1P01</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>1 Feb 2003</date>
<respStmt>
<name>Lou</name>
<resp>Draft</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>First draft</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div><head>Background</head>
<p>The text of the TEI Guidelines (P4) is currently  maintained as an
     XML expression of the original ODD format files used to produce
     P2. This format is increasingly hard to maintain using current
     tools, and is also in need of revision to support new
     facilities, in particular the ability to generate expressions of
     the Guidelines in schema languages other than SGML DTD fragments. </p>
<p>There is a continued need for a simple and accessible
     TEI-conformant means of documenting markup languages in
     general. The TEI tag set for tag set documentation (<xref
      url="../P4X/TD.html">TEI Guidelines, chapter 27</xref>), originally
     proposed for this task, is in need of revision in the light of
     developments in document markup technologies and techniques. It
     also needs to be better integrated with the TEI core tagsets, to
     facilitate use of the TEI as a document authoring environment.
    </p>
<p>The TEI Council has therefore resolved (see  the <xref
      url="tcm04.html">Conference Call on 21 Jan 2003</xref>) to set
      up a <title>Metalanguage task force</title>, charged with the
      objectives and deliverables described in the remainder of this
      document. The task force will be lead by Sebastian Rahtz, and
      will conduct its business according to the Rules and Principles
      for TEI work groups, as documented in <xref
      url="../Drafts/edw54.html">TEI ED W54</xref>, as far as these
      are applicable. </p>
</div>
<div><head>Objectives and deliverables</head>
<list type="ordered">
<item>The ODD format should be revised to be entirely
independent of the XML notation for DTDs</item>
<item>The ODD format and the current TEI  DTD for tag documentation
(TSD) should be re-expressed as a TEI additional module.</item>
<item>The new module should facilitate generation
of  XML DTDs and also of at least one XML schema format. </item>
<item>Tools (e.g. XSLT stylesheets) should be specified which are able
      to
<list><item>automatically convert the current P4 ODDs to 
      the new format</item>
<item>process the new format to produce outputs equivalent to at least
	the current published forms of P4 (i.e. as XML, as HTML, as
	PDF, as XML DTDs, and as Relax NG schema)
       </item>
<item>process the outputs from the previous step in the same way as
	the current Pizza Chef, to allow user production of customized
	TEI views, expressed  as DTDs or schemas, and with
	user-selected documentation </item></list></item>
     </list>
<p>The task force should review the current methods of producing and
     maintaining TEI P4 and make  specific proposals for enhancing
     them in line with the above objectives. A suggested preliminary
     work plan for production of TEI P5 is provided in <xref url="tcw02.html">TC W02</xref>
     which also provides additional background. The work plan for the
     task force will be determined
by agreement of its members, and should be documented either by
     revision of  document TCW02, or by production of a new document, to be maintained by the
     task force chair.</p>
   </div>
<div>
<head>Administrative</head>

<p>The head of the task force is Sebastian Rahtz. Council members who
     have volunteered to participate are Laurent Romary, David Durand,
     and Christian Wittern. Invited experts who have also agreed to
     participate are Norm Walsh and C.M. Sperberg-McQueen.  The Head
     may also invite other appropriate experts to participate at his
     discretion. The TEI Editors are ex officio members of the task
     force, as of all TEI work groups. Other constraints and
     procedures applicable to all TEI work groups are as described in
     document TEI ED W54. </p> 

<p>No budget has been allocated to the task force, but application may
     be made to the Council for one face to face meeting in due
     course. </p>

<p>The task force is required to provide progress reports on its work
regularly to the TEI Technical Council, which has authority for
approving its technical output. </p>

<p>Members of the task force will communicate using a mailing list and
     (optionally) by conference call. Their proceedings should be made
     accessible to any member of the  Council, and decisions
     documented formally on an appropriate part of the TEI web site. </p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Provisional timetable</head>
<p><list>
<item>Review TEI TCW02 and current ODD documentation (4 weeks) </item>
<item>Produce ODD-conformant definition for Son of ODD (6 weeks; due mid May)</item>
<item>Revise Son of ODD specification following Council review (2
       weeks)</item>
<item>Specify, test, and review tools (6 weeks; due July)</item>
<item>Assist editors in production of first draft of P5 (i.e. P4 in
	the new format) in time for Annual Members meeting at end October 2003 </item>
<item>Draft documentation of new format as a TEI module for
	public comment and discussion before submitting as formal
	proposal by January 2004</item>
     </list></p>
<!--
* a revised spec for ODD
 * a conversion of TEI P4 into ODD2
 * a demonstration that this can generate schemes for the TEI
 * a rewrite of the TSD chapter to make that a normal
   tagset, and reunite TSD and ODD
 * some sort of viewpoint on namespaces
-->
   </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
