<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>


<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TCW01: Proposed charter for Feature Structure Workgroup</title>
        <author>Laurent Romary</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>30 Jan 03</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>OUCS</authority>
        <address>
          <email>tei@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the master version of an original document,
created by converting a Word document  TEI XML on 3 Jan 03.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$Date: 2003/01/31 $</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>$Author: lou $</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>$Revision: #2 $</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>28 November 2002</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>Laurent Romary</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>Original draft</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>

<body>

<head>Proposed Charter for Joint ISO-TEI activity on Feature Structures</head>
<note place="foot">This document should be read in conjunction  with
    the draft <xref url="tcw01-iso.htm">New Work Item for ISO TC37/SC4</xref> .</note>

<div><head>Background</head>
<p>The TEI Guidelines contain two complementary chapters on
Feature Structure Representation (chapter 16) and Feature Structure
Declaration Representation (chapter 26). Those two chapters,
originally drafted by Terry Langendoen and Gary Simons, are now
generally recognized as covering many needs in the field of
linguistics.</p>
<p>Moreover, some Natural Language Processing applications have 
provided implementations based on the proposed representations,
which has further increased interest on this specific aspect of the
TEI in this community. It should also be noted that these chapters
are closely integrated with the rest of the TEI scheme, thus
opening up the application of NLP techniques to a very wide
community of users, while at the same time offering the NLP
community access to a real-world range of different text types and
applications</p>
   </div><div>
<head>Proposal</head>
<p>
It is suggested that a revision of the two chapters be
conducted under the auspices of TC37/SC4, and that the
corresponding editorial group
<note place="foot">In ISO terminology, the <soCalled>editor</soCalled> is the person responsible for
moving along a standard proposal up to its final stage. He or she
acts as the head of an editorial group.</note>
be seen as a working group from the
point of view of the TEI.</p>
<p>
The most practical way to do so is simply that the TEI should become an
official liaison to TC37/SC4. As such, it  would  have access to all
documents and debates of the group.</p>
<p>The intention is to work in a more coordinated way than
previously occurred with the terminology working group, where no continuous reporting to
the TEI occurred.</p>
   </div>
<div><head>Constraints resulting from being a TEI working group</head>
<p>
Editing the FS and FSD documents in close connexion with the TEI
consortium would imply that the editors pay careful attention to the
     need to
maintain compatibility with general TEI mechanisms. In revising the
     current proposals, at least the following two 
items should be considered:
<list type="unordered">
<item>Clarification of  alternative strategies. For example, there
exist at present two ways of alternating between features
and  values (the ad hoc vAlt and fAlc vs. the general alt
mechanism): the work group should provide guidance on the
circumstances in which either method might be
preferable;</item>
<item>Compatibility with the final proposals on the use of pointers and
links from the stand-off markup TEI working group. It should be
noted that, more generally, a close collaboration between TC37/SC4
and the TEI must be established on this topic;</item></list>
    </p>
   </div>
<div><head>Constraints resulting from becoming an ISO TC37/SC4 work
item</head>
<p>

Making the revision of the two chapters a TC37/SC4 work
item would have the following consequences:
<list type="unordered">
<item>
It would be necessary to produce a distinct document,  independent of the
general TEI document architecture. Feature structures would be the
actual entry points and some global attributes may have to be
dropped.</item>
<item>
It would oblige the document to be conformant to the general
structure of an ISO standard (with scope, terms and definitions,
etc.);</item>
<item>
It would give additional international visibility to the document,
since it would  be widely distributed to TC37/SC4 members,
thus providing additional sources of comments and suggestions for
modification;</item></list>
    </p>

<p>

The following items have been identified as requiring revision in
the current draft:
<list type="unordered">
<item>
Preliminary formal description of feature structures additional to
what is already provided</item>
<item>
Provision of a simplified representation (FS lite) describing the
basic subset of FS representation without libraries;</item>
<item>
Provision of a re-entrance mechanism;</item>
<item>
Description of typed feature structure</item>
<item>
Simplification of feature value content by replacing some elements
(&lt;symb&gt;, &lt;num&gt; etc.) with references to types
(cf. XML schemas)</item>
<item>
Provision of more NLP related examples (e.g. a syntactic analysis
       using HPSG, a semantic analysis, etc.)
</item></list>
    </p>
   </div>
<div><head>Budget issues</head>
<p>
No specific budget will be requested from the TEI to support those
activities, since  they will be incorporated into 
normal ISO TC37/SC4 activities. Experts participate in ISO work groups on a national
basis.</p>
<p>
As a liaison, the TEI will send specified representatives to all
editorial group meetings (presumably, one of the two
editors).</p>
<p>

Should  a proposal be made to an EU call to fund those
activities, the TEI council would be informed.</p>
   </div>

<div><head>Timetable</head>
<p>

The following timetable is presented as an indication of how things
could be managed within TC37/SC4:
<list type="unordered">
<item>
February 2003: a New Work Item Proposal (NP) together with a first
draft is sent to TC37/SC4 members for approval and comments. This is a good
opportunity to check that the liaison mechanism works</item>
<item>
May 2003: result of voting and compilation of comments</item>
<item>
July 2003: SC4 meeting in conjunction with ACL conference in
Sapporo. Study of comments and decision to proceed to Committee
Draft (CD), or, (if things are going well) as a Draft of
International Standard (DIS)</item>
<item>
November 2003: DIS document, incorporating Sapporo comments, is
sent for vote to TC37 members</item>
<item>Dec. 2004: Publication.</item></list>
    </p>
<p>

A key factor in this timetable will be the speed of reaction to
 comments and provision of updated drafts after plenary SC4
meetings.</p>
   </div>
<div><head>Proposed participants</head>

<p>Editor: Kiyong Lee klee@korea.ac.kr</p>
<p>Members (to be confirmed):
<list>
<item>Syd Bauman Syd_Bauman@brown.edu</item>
<item>
Lou Burnard lou.burnard@oucs.ox.ac.uk</item>
<item>Eric de la Clergerie Eric.De-La-Clergerie@inria.fr</item>
<item>Tomaz Erjavec Tomaz.Erjavec@ijs.si</item>
<item>Ulrich Heid Ulrich.Heid@IMS.Uni-Stuttgart.DE</item>
<item>Terry Langendoen langendt@U.Arizona.EDU</item>
<item>Laurent Romary Laurent.Romary@loria.fr</item>
<item>Gary Simons Gary_Simons@sil.org</item>
     </list></p></div></body>
<!--
This seems to me a little dangerous. It is not reasonable to make
the chapters a standalone documents: the whole point is their
integration with the rest of the Guidelines. I think you would have
to produce the ISO document as a standalone document, following
revision of the chapters. But that seems quite a sensible idea
anyway. </p>
<p>

I don't know what this means.</p>
<p>

Or this. Features structures are already typed.</p>
<p>

This seems dangerous to me. The whole point of the FSD is that the
type system is explicit in the tagging, not delegated to an
external schema</p>
-->

</text>
</TEI.2>

