<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Using the TEI Sourceforge Repository</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>A README file for the Text Encoding Initiative CVS modules.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born Digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$Date: 2008-09-02 10:24:21 +0100 (Tue, 02 Sep 2008) $</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>$Author: rahtz $</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>Initial composition of file.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>$Date: 2008-09-02 10:24:21 +0100 (Tue, 02 Sep 2008) $</date>
        <respStmt>
          <name>$Author: rahtz $</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>Update to reflect current TEI SVN structure and
        makefiles</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Using the TEI Sourceforge Repository</head>
        <div>
          <head>Introduction</head>
          <p> The TEI makes its development files openly available on <xref
              url="http://tei.sourceforge.net/"
            >http://tei.sourceforge.net</xref> so that users can try out
            the latest developments and provide feedback about how they
            think the TEI should develop. This document aims to give a
            brief introduction to using these files directly from the TEI
            Sourceforge Subversion Repository in which they are kept. If you simply
            want to use the most stable versions of the various products of
            the TEI, then investing time and effort in learning to use the
            Repository is probably not what you want to.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>About Version Control</head>
          <p>The Repository uses a Version Control System known as
            Subversion (svn for short). This tool, like its predecessor CVS
            (Concurrent Versions System), is a content versioning tool used
            by many software developers to keep track of changes within
            their source code tree. Subversion provides the means to store
            not only the current version of a file, but a record of all
            changes (and who made those changes) that have occurred to that
            file. Use of Subversion is particularly common on projects
            whose development is being undertaken by those in disparate
            geographical locations, or with multiple developers, since it
            ensures that changes made by one person are not accidentally
            removed when another person posts their changes to the source
            tree. </p>
          <p>The Sourceforge site provides more detailed <xref
              url="http://sourceforge.net/svn/?group_id=106328">information
              about Subversion</xref> and how to use it.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Checking files out of the Repository</head>

          <p>To check out the contents of the TEI Sourceforge Repository
            with a simple Unix subversion client, enter a command like
            this: 
            <code>svn co  https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk ./TEI</code></p>
          <p>This will copy all files from the TEI repository into the
            directory ./TEI. The repository contains several modules, all
            of which will be obtained with this command. If however you
            only want one (say the P5 module), you can do so by including
            the module name: 
            <code> svn co https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk/P5 ./TEI</code></p>
          <p> You can also browse the whole Repository using
            sourceforge&apos;s <xref
              url="http://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/tei/trunk/"
              >web-based Repository viewer</xref>.</p>

        </div>
        <div>
          <head>TEI Packages</head>

          <p> The TEI sf Repository contains files which are grouped into a
            small number of discrete packages for release. The following
            packages are currently maintained: <list type="gloss">
              <label>
                <ref target="Extensions">Extensions</ref>
              </label>
              <item>Extensions and Customisations Development</item>
              <label>
                <ref target="I18N">I18N</ref>
              </label>
              <item>Internationalisation Development </item>
              <label>
                <ref target="P5">P5</ref>
              </label>
              <item>TEI P5 Guidelines and Schema </item>
              <label>
                <ref target="Roma">Roma</ref>
              </label>
              <item>TEI-Conformant Validator (DTD, Relax NG or W3C Schema)
                Creator Development</item>
              <label>
                <ref target="Stylesheets">Stylesheets</ref>
              </label>
              <item>TEI XSLT Stylesheets Development Module</item>
              <label>
                <ref target="tei-emacs">tei-emacs</ref>
              </label>
              <item>TEI Customisation of Emacs Development Module</item>
              <label>
                <ref target="TEIOO">TEIOO</ref>
              </label>
              <item>TEI OpenOffice (and similar) SaveAs TEI XML Filter
                Development Module</item>
              </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Prerequisites for use of TEI Modules</head>
          <p>These packages and their associated Makefiles and scripts are
            all developed and tested on a Debian Linux system. While they
            should work (possibly with customisation) on other Linux
            systems, they are not designed to work on Microsoft Windows. </p>
          <p>If you want to use the scripts provided with these packages,
            we recommend you to install the following additional software
            packages:</p>
          <list type="unordered">
            <item>jing</item>
            <item>perl</item>
            <item>saxon</item>
            <item>trang</item>
            <item>xmllint</item>
            <item>xsltproc</item>
          </list>
        </div>

      </div>
      <div id="Extensions">
        <head>Extensions and Customisations Development Module</head>
        <p> The Extensions and Customisations Development Module provides a
          location for dissemination of well-known Extensions and
          Customisations to the TEI DTD.
          <!--
	  At time of
	writing this includes customisations, usually in ODD format,
	for: <list type="gloss">
	<label>BNC</label>
	<item>The British National Corpus Extensions</item>
	<label>Lampeter</label>
	<item>The Lampeter Corpus of Early Modern English Tracts Extensions </item>
	<label>Lite</label>
	<item>TEI Lite Customisation</item>
	<label>Menota</label>
	<item>The Medieval Nordic Text Archive Extensions</item>
	<label>ProtestantCemetery</label>
	<item>The Protestant Cemetery of Rome Customisations</item>
      </list>
	    -->
        </p>
        <p>None of the customisations or extensions to the TEI should be
          assumed to reflect the current state of the projects, but are
          provided as examples of how others have customised the TEI schema
          in the past. </p>
      </div>
      
      
      <div id="I18N">
        <head>Internationalisation Development Package</head>
        <p> This package produces a location for the dissemination,
          experimentation, and development of TEI&apos;s
          internationalisation movements. Primarily, this consists of the
          translation of elements, attributes, and their descriptions into
          other languages. This allows projects to employ coders using
          their native language to do markup but have it easily translated
          back to international &apos;English&apos; TEI. Current
          languages under development include: English, French, German and
          Spanish. However, others are planned, if you want to help out,
          ask about doing so on the TEI-L mailing list. </p>
      </div>
      <div id="P5">
        <head>P5 Guidelines and Schema Development Package</head>
        <p> This package contains the source files for the development
          version of the TEI Guidelines and associated schemas.  Inside the
          P5 subversion the sources of the English chapters of the Guidelines are in
          <code>Source/Guidelines/en/</code>.  To allow for
          internationalization, if translations of the
          Guidelines are made available they will be located in the same
          place but under their ISO two-letter language code.  The source
          files of the Guidelines also reference separate specifications of
          elements, attributes and classes which are maintained in a
          separate directory <code>Source/Specs/</code> with
          internationlization handled internally.  Each of these files are
          in the TEI ODD (One Document Does it all)
          format. This is a TEI format specifically intended for writing
          guidelines about encoding, from which schemas and reference
          documentation can be automatically extracted.</p>

        <p>As part of the P5 subversion module, a Makefile is provided to
          help generate HTML versions of the TEI
          Guidelines, create compiled schemas and DTDs, amongst various other
          possibilities. There are a number of variables that one can
          change at the beginning of the Makefile. Some of the more
          important of these are: <list
            type="gloss">
            <label>TEISERVER</label>
            <item> This is the eXist server storing TEI files used by the
                <name rend="quoted" type="target">fascicule</name> target.
              Either internet access or a locally served TEI eXist database
              is needed to use this target. By default this is: <xref
                url="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/Query/"
                >http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/Query/</xref>
            </item>
            <label id="P5-PFX">PREFIX</label>
            <item> This is the default location under which you wish to
              install files locally if you use the
              &apos;install&apos; target. By default this is:<rs
                type="path"> /usr</rs>
            </item>
            <label>XSL</label>
            <item> This is the location of the XSLT stylesheets required
              for the transformation of ODD files. By default this points
              to the location of the stylesheets as installed by the TEI
              Debian Packages: <rs type="path"
                >/usr/share/xml/tei/stylesheet</rs> however, if you want to
              use a remote copy of the stylesheets you may wish to change
              this. One option is to use the stylesheets on the TEI
              website: <xref
                url="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/"
                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/stylesheet/</xref> as
              the value of this variable. </item>
            <label>ROMAOPTS</label>
            <item>This variable is used to pass options to Roma such as the
              local source file for the TEI Guidelines. By default this is
              "<code>--localsource=${DRIVER}.xml</code>" </item>
            <label>DRIVER</label>
            <item>This points to the available local source file for the
              TEI Guidelines. By default this is
              "<code>${LANGTREE}/guidelines-${LANGUAGE}.xml</code>", and changing
              LANGTREE and LANGUAGE would allow the generation of the
              guidelines in different languages if the source files for
              those languages exist.</item>
          </list></p>
        <p> The makefile has a number of requirements, these include
          internet access (or a local copy of the stylesheets), and
          up-to-date versions of the perl, jing, trang, xmllint and
          xsltproc programs. If you do not have these installed then many
          of the make targets will not work. Fortunately, there is a target
          which will check to make sure you have these installed:
            <code>make check</code>. Some of the more important targets are
          listed below:</p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <head>Makefile Targets</head>
          <item>
            <label>check</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make check</code></gloss>
            <p> This target checks to see whether you have perl, jing,
              trang, xmllint, and xsltproc installed. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>default</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make</code></gloss>
            <p> This is the default target and creates the TEI P5 schemas
              in RelaxNG &amp; DTD and the HTML version of the
              Guidelines. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>convert</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make convert</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates the TEI P5 schemas in RelaxNG
              &amp; DTD. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>dtds</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make dtds</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates DTDs for TEI P5 in the DTD/ directory.
            </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>schemas</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make schemas</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates RelaxNG Schemas for TEI P5 in the
              Schema/ directory. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>html</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make html</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates an HTML version of the TEI Guidelines
              in the Guidelines/ directory. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>xml</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make xml</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates a TEI Lite (P5) XML version of the
              Guidelines as Guidelines.xml in the current directory (i.e.,
              P5/) as well as also making the exemplars listed further
              below.</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>split</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make split</code></gloss>
            <p> This target creates a set of TEI P5 ODD files, with entities
              resolved, that are a version of the Guidelines split into
              chapters, in the split/ directory. </p>
          </item>
          <!--	  <item>
	    <label>exist</label>
	    <gloss>Usage: <code>make exist</code></gloss>
	    <p> This target updates a locally running copy of the eXist XML database with the TEI
	    files. The files are added via the SOAP interface and the database is assumed to be
	    running at: <xref
	    url="http://localhost:8080/exist">http://localhost:8080/exist</xref>
	    </p>
	  </item>
-->
          <item>
            <label>clean</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make clean</code></gloss>
            <p> This target removes most of the files created by the other
              targets. </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>install</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make install</code></gloss>
            <p> This target installs a separate local copy of the DTDs,
              Schema, and HTML version of the guidelines under the file
              path given by the PREFIX variable (see <ptr target="P5-PFX"
              />, above) . </p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>exemplars</label>
            <gloss>Usage: <code>make exemplars</code></gloss>
            <p> This target uses Roma to create the DTDs and Schemas from a
              number of exemplary ODD files in the <code>Exemplars</code>
              directory.   The exemplars target will create DTDs, XML Schemas,
              and both compact and xml versions of RelaxNG Schemas for the
              customizations based on the following ODD files:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                <label>tei_all.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with maximal setup</gloss>
                <p>The full TEI setup with almost everything you could possibly
                  want included.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_corpus.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with corpus</gloss>
                <p>An example setup for basic copora using TEI or
                  teiCorpus as the starting element.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_dictionaries.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI customization for dictionaries</gloss>
                <p>An experimental customization of the TEI for
                  Dictionaries, this ODD includes a detailed example of
                  the addition of an element.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_drama.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with drama</gloss>
                <p>An example setup which includes drama and linking
                  modules.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_examples.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI for TEI examples</gloss>
                <p>This ODD demonstrates the creation of <gi>egXML</gi>
                  with the inclusion of MathML and RelaxNG as
                  possibilities.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>teilite.odd</label>
                <gloss>The TEI Lite customization</gloss>
                <p>This is the ODD for the popular example customization
                  TEI Lite.  It is entitled "Encoding for Interchange: an
                  introduction to the TEI".
                </p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_minimal.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with minimal setup</gloss>
                <p> A very minimal TEI customization, with only the
                  header, core, tei and textstructure modules.  If you
                  only want to use elements that appear in the core
                  modules, then this is the customization for you!
                </p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_ms.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI for manuscript description</gloss>
                <p>This example customization for manuscript description
                  includes, in addition to the basic modules, those for
                  names and dates, transcription, and manuscript
                  description.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_odd.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with ODD elements</gloss>
                <p>This customization adds the ODD (One Document Does
                  it all) tagset documentation module and changes the
                  content of egXML. </p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <label>tei_oucs.odd</label>
                <gloss>TEI with OUCS setup</gloss>
                <p>This complex customization is given as an example of
                  how the Oxford University Computing Services use the
                  TEI for authoring its website.  See <xref
                    url="http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/">http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/</xref>
                  to see documents validated against schemas generated from this ODD.</p>
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div id="Roma">
        <head>Roma: TEI-Conformant Validator (DTD, Relax NG or W3C Schema)
          Creator Development </head>

        <p> The Roma tool allows creation of TEI-Conformant Validators in
          the form of DTD, Relax NG or W3C Schemas. This can be used to
          customise the TEI Schema by adding, removing, renaming elements
          and/or attributes. This can also be used to generate specialised
          documentation for this customisation containing only the elements
          specified, or can be output in foreign languages if available. Roma uses TEI
          P5 and (in addition to its command-line version available in the
          Roma subversion module) there is also a web
          interface at <xref url="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Roma/"
            >http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/</xref> which allows an easy
          form-filling method of generating the schemas and documentation.
          Roma uses the ODD format as its base and so any customisations
          can be saved in this form for later re-use or refinement. </p>
      </div>
      <div id="Stylesheets">
        <head>TEI XSL Stylesheets Package </head>
        <p> This package provides a location for the dissemination and
          development of XSLT stylesheets produced by the TEI. The <xref
            url="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/wiki/">TEI Wiki</xref> provides a
          location for stylesheets produced by others for TEI documents.</p>

        <p> The TEI XSL Stylesheets enable one to transform XML documents
          to HTML, to LaTeX, and to XSL Formatting Objects. The latter two
          of these are frequently used to transform TEI XML into PDF
          format. The XSL FO style sheets were developed for use with
          PassiveTeX (<xptr url="http://www.tei-c.org/Software/passivetex/"
          />, a system using XSL formatting objects to render XML to PDF
          via LaTeX, and have also been tested with Render X and Antenna
          House implementations.</p>

        <p> Significantly more detailed information is available concerning
          the TEI XSL Stylesheets on the TEI website <xref
            url="http://www.tei-c.org/Stylesheets/teic/"
            >http://www.tei-c.org/Stylesheets/teic/</xref> and advice is
          available via the TEI-L mailing list. </p>
        <p> The Makefile provided with the TEI XSL Stylesheets has no
          default make target. The most usable two make targets are: <list
            type="gloss">
            <label>install</label>
            <item>Installs the P4 and P5 xsl stylesheets in <rs type="path"
                >/usr</rs> or wherever you have set the
              &apos;PREFIX&apos; variable at the beginning of the
              Makefile.</item>
            <label>dist</label>
            <item>This creates a release subdirectory of both P4 and P5
              sets of files.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p> For the more technically interested, the stylesheets have
          internal documentation, using <xref
            url="http://www.pnp-software.com/">P&amp;P
            Software&apos;s</xref> XSLTdoc system; the results can be
          browsed in the <xref
            url="http://www.tei-c.org/Stylesheets/teic/xsltdoc/">on the
            technical documetation section of the TEI Stylesheets
          website</xref>. </p>
      </div>
      <div id="tei-emacs">
        <head>TEI Customisation of Emacs</head>
        <p>This package is a setup for the widely used open source GNU
          Emacs editor to provide a single all-singing all-dancing TEI
          Editing Environment. The files included are Elisp packages; a
          Debian package is available for installation on Linux, where it
          will interact with existing TEI and Emacs setups. For MS-Windows
          a complete self-contained package of Emacs and all the TEI
          stylesheets and setup is available (<xptr
            url="http://www.tei-c.org/Software/tei-emacs/"/>).</p>
        <p>TEI Emacs is maintained by Sebastian Rahtz (Oxford) and
          Christian Wittern (Kyoto). Its main intention is to provide a
          good basic editing environment for TEI files. It uses NXML mode
          to provide continual incremental schema-based validation. For
          more information on installation and use of tei-emacs see <xref
            url="http://www.tei-c.org/Software/tei-emacs/"
            >http://www.tei-c.org/Software/tei-emacs/</xref>.</p>
      </div>
      <div id="TEIOO">
        <head>TEI OpenOffice (and similar) SaveAs TEI XML Filter
          Development Package</head>
        <p> This package brings together various filters for saving
          word-processing documents as TEI XML. There are currently filters
          to and from OpenOffice and TEI Lite, but there are plans for some
          filters for Microsoft Word. For more information on installation of the TEI -
          OpenOffice filters see <xptr
            url="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Software/teioo/"/>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div id="example">
        <head>Example: Installation of Stylesheets, P5, and Roma packages</head>

        <p> This is a step-by-step example of installation of the
          Stylesheets, P5, and Roma packages. This should give most people
          a working copy of the main TEI deliverables. These steps assume a
          linux system and command-line svn client, and installs everything
          in the "/tmp/tei/" directory. You should modify this to reflect
          where you want to put things on your particular system. </p>

        <list type="ordered">
          <item>
            <label>Create and move into a directory for your TEI files</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>mkdir /tmp/tei ; cd /tmp/tei </code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Check out a copy of Stylesheets package</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>svn co https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk/Stylesheets ./Stylesheets</code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Check out a copy of P5 package</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>svn co https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk/P5 ./P5</code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Check out a copy of Roma package</label>
            <lb/>
            
            <code>svn co https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk/Roma ./Roma </code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Go into Stylesheets directory and install the
              stylesheets</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>cd Stylesheets ; make PREFIX=/tmp/tei install ; cd ..
            </code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Go into Roma directory and install Roma</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>cd Roma ; make PREFIX=/tmp/tei install ; cd .. </code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Go into P5 directory and install the TEI Guidelines and Schemas</label>
            <lb/>
            <code>cd P5 ; make PREFIX=/tmp/tei XSL=/tmp/tei/share/xml/tei/stylesheet install ; cd .. </code>
          </item>
          <item>
            <label>Go into P5 directory and create the exemplar DTDs and
              Schemas</label><lb/>
            <code>cd P5; make exemplars; cd ..</code>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>This should provide you with a working TEI hierarchy in
          /tmp/tei/ (or whatever you changed that to on each command) with
          the TEI P5 Guidelines and Schemas, the TEI XSL Stylesheets, and a
          copy of Roma.  It should also leave you a copy of the schemas for
          the most popular TEI customizations in
          <code>P5/Exemplars/</code>.  More information on using these deliverables is
          available from the TEI website. </p>
        <p><emph>Note</emph>: It is also possible to
          retrieve all of the modules from the TEI subversion repository
          with:  
          <code>svn co https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk ./TEI</code> 
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
