<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="/teixlite.css"?>
<!--DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
"http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd" []-->
<TEI.2>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Draft Charge for the Work Group on Character Encoding </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
<p>For TEI website</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
<p>Original</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <!-- one of (change list) -->
   <change>
    <date>14 Apr 2002</date>
    <respStmt>
<name>Lou</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Revised</item>
   </change>
 <change>
    <date>2 Jul 2001</date>
    <respStmt>
<name>Lou</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Drafted</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>

<front>
<titlePage>
<docTitle>
<titlePart>Draft Charge for the Workgroup on Character Encoding</titlePart>
<titlePart>TEI ED W72</titlePart>
</docTitle>
<docDate>14 April 2002</docDate>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body>
<div><head>Objectives</head>
<list type="ordered">
<item>Reformulate this list of objectives.</item>
<item>Review thoroughly all aspects of the recommendations
   currently presented in TEI P4 with respect to the encoding of
   character-level information and of writing systems in general;</item>
     <item>Make specific proposals for changes in the existing
   recommendations which will better align the TEI Recommendations
   with current needs and practices in the widest text enoding
   community;</item> 
<item>Draft new
   recommendations in areas not at present addressed explicitly or adequately by the
       Guidelines; such areas include (but are not limited to)
<list>
<item>mechanisms for the definition of character semantics in a Unicode context;</item>
<item>assessment of input and display software for multilingual work;</item>
<item>best practice in the standardized encoding of manuscript	materials;</item>
      </list></item>
<item>Respond to comments on the relevant portions of TEI P4
    routed to this work group by the editors.</item>
</list></div>
<div>
<head>Administrative</head>

<p>The initial membership of this workgroup included the following:
<list>
<item>Christian Wittern, Kyoto University (wittern@kanji.zinbun.kyoto-u.ac.jp) : chair</item>
<item>Deborah Anderson, Berkeley (dwanders@socrates.berkeley.edu) </item>
<item>David Birnbaum, Pittsburgh University (djbpitt+@pitt.edu)</item>
<item>Patrick Durusau, Emory University (pdurusau@emory.edu) </item>
</list>
The chair should specify current membership as soon as possible, for ratification by the
     TEI Board at its next meeting. The TEI Editors are ex officio
     members of all TEI Work Groups. Other constraints and procedures
     applicable to all TEI Work Groups are described in document TEI
     ED W54. </p>
<p>The group has a budget of USD 8000 for the year ending 2003, during
     which one meeting is authorized. </p>
<p>The Work group is required to provide  progress reports on its work regularly
to the TEI Technical Council, which has authority for approving
all technical output from the work group. </p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Deadlines</head>
<p>(To be agreed with WG head):
<list>
<item>Reformulation of objectives and recruitment of work
       group members should be completed by 1 May 2002, in time for the TEI Board meeting May 9th;</item>
<item>A preliminary work plan should be prepared by 1 August 2002</item>
<item>A first draft of recommendations for revisions and additions required to P4
       should be prepared by 15 September 2002, for review by the TEI
       Council meeting of 11 Oct 2002.</item>
<item>The final reports from the Workgroup should be completed by 1
       January 2003</item>
     </list></p>
   </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
