<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!--DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite P4 XML 2002-05//EN" 
"http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd"
 []-->
<!-- "/usr/local/lib/sgml/TEI/P4/teixlite.dtd" -->
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>TEI ED W 78 (draft)</title>
	<title>Public Comment and Update Procedure for TEI Proposals</title>
	<author>Syd Bauman</author>
	<author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<p>This draft is for use of the TEI Editors and Council, not
	for public consumption. </p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>None</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<list>
<item><date>10 Feb 03</date>: LB further revisions </item>
<item><date>24 Nov 02</date>: LB minor revisions </item>
<item><date>22 Nov 02</date>: SB Drafted </item>
   </list>
  </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="section">
	<head>Introduction</head>
	<p>The Text Encoding Initiative Consortium (TEI-C) already has
	  mechanisms in place 
	  <list>
	    <item>to effect major strategic technical changes to the
	      <title>Guidelines</title>, (e.g. adding new chapters or
	      overhauling existing ones, deciding on what
	      metalanguage(s) will be used, specific major issues like
	      character encoding etc). Such changes are the
	      responsibility of the TEI Council, mostly by
	      commissioning work groups</item>
	    <item>to correct corrigible errors in the
	      <title>Guidelines</title>; such changes are generally
	      effected by the Editors on their own.</item>
	  </list> But there does not exist any mechanism for
	  considering and effecting changes that are in between:
	      i.e. not arising from something demonstrably erroneous, but
	  too minor to require a work group be commisioned. Examples
	      might be to 
	  eliminate the <gi>dateRange</gi>> and <gi>timeRange</gi>
	      elements; to change the verse and drama tagsets to be
	      additional instead of base; to provide a few extra
	      elements  for encoding archival correspondence.</p>
	<p>This document suggests a mechanism both for users of the
	  TEI scheme to recommend such changes, and for the TEI-C to
	  consider and implement them.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
	<head>Proposals for Amendments</head>
	<p>Users can submit a proposal for an amendment at will via
	  the web. The interface is yet to be determined, but it will
	  probably involve a web-form or submission of an XML file,
	conforming to a specification yet to be determined by the
	editors.
<!-- In either case the end result
	  is a document conforming to a TEI DTD designed by the
	  editors for this purpose.</p>
	<note resp="sbauman.emt">Lou, there should be a section in the
	  proposal format for whether or not there is a natural source
	  of funding for work on this issue, no?</note> --></p>
	<p>Proposals for Amendment do not have to be very technical or
	  very detailed, but should be clear and coherent. They should
	contain, at a minimum, the following information:
<list>
<item>A clear description of  the
	  problems or shortcomings which need to be addressed</item>
      <item>A clear summary of any proposed modification to the
	  Guidelines which would address the stated problem</item>
      <item>name and contact information of the proposer</item>
      <item>name and contact information of someone willing to work on
	  implementing the proposal (may be the same person as the proposer)</item>
<item>An estimate of the likely consequences of implementing the
	  proposal</item>
<item>An estimate of the likely amount of work involved in implementing the proposal</item>
     </list>
    </p>
<p>The editors will check all submitted proposals, and will jointly
	  determine whether or not the proposal is complete and worthy
	  of further
	  consideration. This is the <soCalled>grand jury</soCalled> stage,
	  which is intended to weed out complete crackpot or spam
	  requests (e.g., that the TEI should devote a base tag set to
	  the encoding of the recorded mating calls of extinct
	  species). It doesn't take much to pass muster here, but
	  those that don't are not even submitted to publicly
	  available scrutiny.</p>
    <p>On acceptance, the editors will register the Proposal for
	  Change in a TEI standing document, using a format to be
	  determined. </p>
<!--
	<p>The completed version is assigned a TEI document number
	  (perhaps TEI LL NNNN, where LL is "PA" for "proposal for
	  amendment" or "RC" for "request for consideration"?) and
	  checked into a publicly accessible TEI document
	  repository.</p>
-->
<p>It is the job of the Council to determine dispositionl of Proposals
     for Change. At least twice a year, the Council will consider the
     merits of all currently submitted proposals in a gathered field,
     and determine their disposition. Likely outcomes for a proposal
     are one of the following:
<list type="ordered">
      <item>it is inappropriate to proceed further with the proposal
       because it is out of scope for the TEI Guidelines,  technically
       flawed, or prohibitively complex or expensive</item>
      <item>the proposal needs further technical work before it can be
       integrated into or used to modify the current Guidelines</item>
      <item>The proposal identifies a modification or other course of
       action which can be integrated directly into the current
       Guidelines</item>
     </list> The Council may identify other kinds of disposition in
     the light of experience, but these seem the most probable.</p>
<p>The editors will record the Council's decision on each proposal in
     its associated documentation, and these will be available as a
     matter of public record from the TEI web site.  
Taking each type of disposition in turn, <!-- The editors are not sure of the most effective way
	of combining efficient disposal with accountability. Here is
	one (fairly complex) procedure which might work: -->
<list>
	<item>In the case of a rejected proposal, the  Council will
	  supply the editors with explanation of their grounds for the
	  decision for inclusion in the documentation. No further
	  action is taken.</item>
	<item>In the case of a proposal needing further work, the
	  Council will assign at least one of its members
	  to work with the person indicated in the proposal and with the
	  editors to carry out such further work. Once the work is
	  completed, the proposal is resubmitted to the Council, in
	  the same way as any other proposal.</item>
        <item>In the case of a proposal not needing further work, the
	  editors will proceed directly to implementation, without
	  further reference to the Council.</item>
<item>When a  proposal for change is implemented, its associated
	  record will be integrated into the change list for the
	  relevant edition of the Guidelines. </item>
     </list>
<!--
	<item>These three to five people, without a budget, flesh out a
	  proposed amendment (or draft amendment). This draft
	  amendment should be as detailed as possible, perhaps even
	  containing recommended rewording of the relevant sections of
	  the <title>Guidelines</title>.</item>
	<item>The draft amendment is posted publicly in the same
	  repository as the proposal for amendment <note>Does it
	    replace the proposal?</note>. The Council is reminded
	  about or notified of it at least 2 weeks prior to one of
	  their meetings (regular face-to-face meeting, regular
	  conference call, or a special conference call initiated for
	  the purpose of considering the proposed amendment.</item>
	<item>Council votes on amendment, either accepting it as is,
	rejecting it outright, or sending it back to the mini work
	group for revision. The Council can suggest revisions, but
	  generally shouldn't modify the draft itself <note>I'm not
	sure of this procedure</note></item>
	<item>Editors effect accepted changes. Proposal for amendment and
	  proposed amendment document are moved off of main such
	  repository into an archive.</item>
     </list>
    </p>
<p>The Council is requested to consider whether this proposal is
     appropriate or desirable.</p>
-->
    </p>      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-system-identifiers-are-preferred:t
End:
-->
