<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../Stylesheets/teixlite.css"?>
<!--DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
                       "../Lite/DTD/teixlite.dtd" [
   <!ATTLIST xptr url CDATA #IMPLIED >
   <!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED >
   ]-->
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Version numbering of TEI Guidelines</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Currently unpublished for TEI Council and editors' use.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Use of Version number of TEI Guidelines</head>
      <p>During its conference call of <date value="2004-01-27">27 Jan
          04</date> the TEI Council agreed that:
        <list>
          <item>conformant documents should specify the version of the
            TEI to which they conform by means of an attribute named
            <ident>version</ident></item>
          <item>its value should follow the pattern
            <hi>major.minor.micro</hi>, with numeric values. 
          </item>
          <item>guidelines on version numbering should be agreed by
            the editors and documented ASAP</item>
        </list><bibl><xptr
            url="../Council/tcm09.html#id2633880"/></bibl> This
        working paper proposes guidelines for version numbering of the
        Guidelines.</p>
      <div type="section">
        <head>When</head>
        <p>The version number should be updated whenever a
          user-visible change is made to the content of the
          Guidelines, whether that change is due to a change to the
          source ODD files or to a change in the stylesheets that
          produce the human-readable Guidelines or schemas.</p>
        <p>But perhaps more useful than discussing when the version
          number is updated is to mention when it is not updated. The
          version number should not be updated when a change is made
          to the stylesheets that produce the Guidelines or schema
          from the source ODDs that changes only format, not content.
          Furthermore changes to Roma or other software that assist
          TEI users should not cause a change in the version number of
          the Guidelines.</p>
        <p>So the following changes should not result in an updated
          version number:
          <list>
            <item>a change to the stylesheets that changed the
              presentation of attribute values from fixed font to
              bold;</item>
            <item>a correction of a typo in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of
              the ODD source of the Guidelines.<note type="internal"
                resp="sb" place="inline" anchored="yes">Lou — do
                we like this corollary? — sb</note></item>
            <item>a bug fix to Roma which corrected a problem that
              caused incorrect DTD fragments to be generated if the
              additional tag-set for names &amp; dates was
              selected</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head>What</head>
        <p>The version number will be a <soCalled>dotted
            triad</soCalled> in the form <q>major.minor.micro</q>.
          Each of <rs>major</rs>, <rs>minor</rs>, and <rs>micro</rs>
          is an integer. (I.e., as is common with such version
          numbering systems, leading zeroes may have to be inserted
          before string comparison can usefully be performed.)</p>
        <p>The three components are updated as follows.
          <list>
            <item><label>micro</label> gets incremented whenever there
              is a user-visible content change that:
              <list>
                <item>does not alter the set of documents that conform
                  to the Guidelines (i.e., makes no syntactic change
                  to the constraints prescribed), <emph>or</emph></item>
                <item>does not alter the <emph>intended</emph> set of
                  documents that conform to the Guidelines, but rather
                  only changes the set that actually do conform by
                  correcting an error; and</item>
                <item>does not significantly alter the semantics of
                  conforming documents, <emph>or</emph></item>
                <item>alters the semantics of conforming documents by
                  correcting an error.</item>
              </list>
            </item>
            <item><label>minor</label> gets incremented whenever there
              is a user-visible change that is not a large enough
              change to alter the existing chapter numbering, which
              changes the syntax or semantics of conforming documents
              other than minor error correction. When <rs>minor</rs>
              is incremented, <rs>micro</rs> is set to zero.</item>
            <item><label>major</label> gets incremented for major
              revisions of the Guidelines. At such increments chapter
              numbering, syntax specifications, etc. may change in
              significant ways. <rs>Major</rs> changes are not
              necessarily backwards compatible. When <rs>major</rs> is
              incremented both <rs>minor</rs> and <rs>micro</rs> are
              set to zero.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="section">
        <head>Examples</head>
        <p><table>
            <row>
              <cell>change to Guidelines or stylesheets</cell>
              <cell>change to version number</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Correct typo in <gi>teiHeader</gi></cell>
              <cell>none</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Correct typo in <gi>text</gi> of Guidelines</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>micro</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Change stylesheet so that section headings are
                larger in the PDF version and centered in the HTML
                version</cell>
              <cell>none</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Fix stylesheet so that the list of elements in the
                <q>may occur within</q> listings in reference section
                are sorted by class, not just alphabetically</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>micro</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Fix stylesheet so that a newline is inserted
                between each set of elements in a given class in the
                <q>may occur within</q> listings in reference section</cell>
              <cell>none</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Correct the name of the
                <ident>referencesystem</ident> class to <ident>referenceSystem</ident></cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>micro</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>After much discussion on TEI-L, change the largest
                <gi>divN</gi> from 7 to 9</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>minor</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Add a new section at the end of the feature
                structure chapter with a few examples of using FSs to
                encode meta information about dying languages</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>minor</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>After receiving a complaint that a particular
              example was offensive, change to a different example</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>micro</rs></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Add a new chapter on the encoding of legal documents</cell>
              <cell>increment <rs>major</rs></cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
