<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Lite from P4 to P5: Continuity and Change</title>
	    <title>TEI ED W85</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>December 2004</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Draft for publication as preface to Ciotti's new translation
	    of the TEI Lite tutorial.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Original, with some material from talks given in Wuerzburg and Baltimore.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>$Date: 2008-09-02 10:24:21 +0100 (Tue, 02 Sep 2008) $.</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>$Author: rahtz $</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>$Revision: 483 $</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
<text>
<!--<front>
<div type="abstract">
<p>This article gives an overview of  the origin, current state, and future, of
TEI Lite.  </p>
</div>
</front>-->
<body>

<head>TEI Lite from P4 to P5: Continuity and Change</head>

<div><head>The Story So Far</head>

<p>In November 1987, representatives from forty or so academic
institutions and projects converged on Vassar College in upstate New
York. They shared a common vision: the transformation of substantial
amounts of the world's literature into computer-readable form; but
what had brought them together was the lack of agreed international
standards in the production of what was at that time called
<soCalled>machine-readable text</soCalled>. Over two wintry days, they
considered the cacophony of different practices emerging in the
service of that common vision at institutions already existing across
the US, across Europe, and in Japan, but scattered and fragmented in
those pre-World Wide Web days. The Internet as a social phenomenon was
approaching adolescence: it had not yet established itself outside the
world of academic research, and the technical standards needed to move
it forward were still only dimly perceived. </p>

<p>In the early nineties, the Text Encoding Initiative was formed as
an international research project, with funding from the US National
Endowment for the Humanities, the European Union, the Canadian Social
Science Research Council, and the Andrew W Mellon Foundation. The TEI
was jointly sponsored by three established international professional
associations, which established a small management committee, and
appointed two <soCalled>editors</soCalled> to co-ordinate the
enthusiastic participation of more than a hundred scholars
worldwide. Its remit was to attempt a complete definition of current
practice and to produce recommendations or Guidelines for the creation
and usage of electronic texts in key linguistic and literary
disciplines. The first research phases of the TEI came to an end in
1994 with the publication of TEI P3, the <soCalled>big green
books</soCalled> which over the next few years were to become the
reference standard for the building of the digital library.</p>

<p>At the start of the current century, the TEI re-established itself
as a membership consortium<note place="foot">For details, see the TEI
Consortium web site at <xptr url="http://www.tei-c.org"/></note>,
jointly hosted by two US and two European Universities, and sponsored
a first major revision of the TEI Guidelines. This edition, known as
TEI P4, was a <soCalled>maintenance release</soCalled>, bringing the
Guidelines up to date with changes in the technical infrastructure — 
most notably in the use of the W3C's Extensible Markup Language (XML)
as its means of expression<note place="foot">This was particularly
appropriate in that one of the editors of the XML standard, Michael
Sperberg-McQueen, had also served as editor of the original TEI
Guidelines.</note> rather than the ISO standard SGML. TEI P4 was
published in 2002, under the imprint of the University of Virginia
Press, and forms the current reference standard for the TEI
Guidelines.</p>

<p>However, nothing written in digital form is ever really
finished. Since 2002, work has been proceeding on the next major
revision of the TEI Guidelines, to be known as TEI P5, which will
include far more substantive changes than were needed for P4. This
preface sketches some of the changes anticipated in this new release
and also how these will affect the TEI Lite subset described in the
remainder of the present publication.</p>

</div>

<div><head>TEI Lite</head>

<p>The goals of the TEI were to facilitate better interchange and
integration of scholarly textual data, in all languages, and from all
periods. As such the TEI had two inherently contradictory objectives:
on the one hand, to deliver <soCalled>guidance for the
perplexed</soCalled> by suggesting <emph>what</emph> textual features
should be encoded in a document; on the other, to provide assistance for
the specialist by suggesting <emph>how</emph> any particular set of
textual phenomena might be encoded. Its remit was thus to be both a
user-driven codification of existing best practice, and also a loose
framework into which unpredictable extensions might be fitted. Its
recommendations thus cover both generic text structures and some
highly specific areas based on (but not limited by) existing
practice.</p>

<p>The original scope of the TEI was encyclopaedic, embracing not just
the basic structural and functional components of running text but
also diplomatic transcription of non-digital textual (and aural)
sources, images, and annotation thereof; links, correspondence, and
alignment of encoded objects; data-like objects such as dates, times,
places, persons, events (what is now termed <soCalled>named entity
recognition</soCalled>); meta-textual annotations (correction,
deletion, etc); linguistic analysis of all kinds and at all levels;
contextual metadata of all kind. No-one requires all of this, yet all
of it is required by someone.  Considerable effort and ingenuity was
therefore invested in ways of making it possible to derive multiple
views (DTDs or schemas) from the enormous set of textual categories or
distinctions identified by the Guidelines, which (as of TEI P4)
documented 362 distinct XML elements, 95 attributes, and 88 classes,
grouped into 24 distinct modules of various kinds.  To
demonstrate that this polymorphic architecture actually worked, the
TEI editors used it to produce TEI Lite, one specific customization
which turned out to have a life of its own. </p>

<p>TEI Lite was intended to meet three goals. The first was to provide
a subset of the TEI Recommendations which would be adequate to the
needs of most likely users of the whole of the TEI most of the
time. To decide on that subset, we began by looking at sample texts
gathered together in the Oxford Text Archive and at other digital
projects which had been represented at the Poughkeepsie conference. We
then listed the textual features which these sample texts marked up,
and selected the corresponding TEI elements for inclusion in TEI
Lite. The second goal was to provide a subset of elements rich enough
to support an authoring environment for the production of online
documentation such as the Guidelines themselves. Here, we were guided
simply by our own experience as editors of the hundreds of working
papers, published articles, and reference materials that had gone into
the production of TEI P1 to P3 inclusive. And finally TEI Lite was
conceived of as a practical demonstration of the customization
facilities of the TEI scheme — and therefore had to provide some
features which were <emph>not</emph> otherwise included in it.</p>
 
<p>Despite the protestations of the TEI editors and others, however,
TEI Lite was occasionally perceived as being <emph>the</emph>
recommended introduction to the TEI scheme for all purposes. Widely
translated, its manual came to form the basis of many introductory
tutorials and workshops<note place="foot">See <xptr
url="http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/"/></note>, as well as to define the
practice of many major encoding projects, particularly in the digital
library community. This was a mixed blessing: TEI Lite is (inevitably)
lacking in elements some projects will consider essential, and (even
more inevitably) over-supplied with elements other projects will never
wish to use. Because the customization methods by which TEI Lite was
constructed remain somewhat arcane to the non-SGML specialist, there
was a tendency for projects to edit TEI Lite itself in nonstandard and
unpredictable ways to produce <soCalled>TEI Lite like</soCalled>
schemas, thus seriously compromising the interchangeability of their
resources. More worryingly, it came to be perceived in some quarters
as the TEI's final word on what <soCalled>text</soCalled>
<emph>really</emph> is: though any careful reading of the TEI
Guidelines proper would show the extent to which the TEI tries to
problematize this notion, by emphasizing the relativity of the shared
assumptions and priorities about the digital agenda which underly its
suggestions. Those priorities, specifically the focus on content and
function (rather than presentation), and the identification of generic
solutions (rather than application-specific ones) have stood the test
of time. But they are not necessarily universal.</p>
</div>

<div><head>The next generation</head>

<p>When the production of TEI P5 was first announced, its goals were
declared to be threefold: firstly, it was clear that an internal audit
of some kind was long overdue; after a decade of use, some of its
recommendations surely were in need of review. Secondly, it was
equally clear that the TEI was no longer the only digital text game in
town (if it ever had been) and that it needed to review its ability to
fit into a joined-up wired world. And thirdly, some new application areas
have emerged for digital technologies in the scholarly world to which
the TEI was uniquely qualified to make an original contribution, such
as the encoding and cataloguing of manuscript sources. </p>

<p>As of this writing, TEI P5 is still a work in progress, but some
general principles have become clear, as have some specifics. TEI P5
schemas will continue to be expressible in both XML DTD syntax and the
W3C Schema Language, but TEI P5 is primarily organized as an
application of the ISO standard schema language RelaxNG. Many of the
complexities in the original TEI architecture resulting from the use
of SGML have been removed. Over the last two years, TEI Workgroups
have made substantive recommendations on the following topics:
<list>

<item>best practice in using the ISO 10646 standard, including the
documentation of non-standard character and variant glyph usage,
replacing the old recommendations on using SGML character entities and
the Writing System Declaration;</item>

<item>development of a completely new XML-based version of the TEI's
original <soCalled>literate programming</soCalled> system, which
supports automatic generation of documentation and schemas from a
single reference XML source, replacing the old ODD and tagdoc system;</item>
<item>development of a new manuscript description module, building on
and harmonizing work undertaken in a number of other research
projects, notably the EU-funded MASTER project;</item>

<item>revision and rationalisation of the recommendations on hypertext
linking to take advantage of new W3C standards such as Xlink and
Xpointer, replacing the old distinction between internal and external
linking methods and the TEI Extended Pointer Syntax;</item>

<item>revision and simplification of the recommendations for
representation of linguistic analysis expressed as feature structures;
this work has been done jointly with an ISO working group reporting
to ISO TC 37/SC4 and is on track for international standardization
as ISO CD 26410-1</item>
</list></p>

<p>In addition, and in response to a public call for  proposals for
revision, a number of other minor modifications are anticipated. These
include:
<list>
<item>a major revision and rationalization of the TEI class
system</item>
<item>new meta-textual elements <gi>choice</gi> and <gi>combine</gi>
(discussed below)</item>
<item>revision and expansion of the prosopographic elements</item>
<item>revision of the elements for structured bibliographic descriptions</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Almost all of the proposed changes may be seen as motivated by the
need to make the TEI scheme more interoperable with the new digital
world which it has, in part, created.  Many other communities have
worked in the areas first addressed by the TEI since 1987, and much of
that work is of direct relevance and benefit to the TEI community. In
addition to the W3C and ISO standards already mentioned, other
complementary XML-based vocabularies such as MathML, SVG and Docbook
have emerged in the last decade, which the TEI user community cannot
afford to ignore, to say nothing of other conceptual models and
metadata schemata. At the same time, there remains scope for the TEI
to continue to innovate where necessary. In retrospect, much of what
was experimental in TEI P4 has since become mainstream (a good example
is the TEI Extended Pointer Syntax), but much has also simply remained
experimental, or been overtaken by events. A major part of the TEI P5
process has therefore been a focus on better tools for managing
evolutionary change in the document and its derived schemas, which (it
is hoped) will make the production of this and future versions both
simpler and more transparent, as well as providing more user-friendly
tools for customization.</p>

<p>As noted above, the TEI Guidelines, its DTD, and its schema
fragments, are all produced from a single XML resource containing:

<list  type="ordered">
<item>a lot of descriptive prose</item>
<item>many usage examples</item>
<item>formal declarations for components of the TEI Abstract
Model, specifically <list>
<item>modules</item>
<item>elements and attributes</item>
<item>classes and macros</item>
</list></item>
</list>
</p>

<p>We call this resource an ODD (One Document Does it all) although it
is actually instantiated as a large number of XML mini-documents.<note
place="foot">For technical detail see further <title>RelaxNG with Son
of ODD</title>: paper presented at Extreme Markup Language
Conferences, Montreal 2004; available from <ptr
url="http://www.mulberrytech.com/Extreme/Proceedings/html/2004/Burnard01/EML2004Burnard01.pdf"/></note>. Unlike
previous versions of ODD, this version has no dependency on any
particular schema language, and can thus generate customized schemas
in DTD, RelaxNG, or W3C Schema Language. XSLT stylesheets and other
tools have been developed to support the extraction of customized
documentation from it, to support internationalization of the
underlying modules, and even to provide mappings between its
conceptual model and that of other conceptual ontologies.</p>

<p>Technical details are out of scope for this brief paper, but it is
worth stressing the extent to which it has greatly simplified the
customization layer of the TEI. To define a view of the TEI scheme,
one now produces a simple XML document, using a vocabulary defined as
an integral part of the Guidelines.  For example: 
<eg><![CDATA[
<schemaSpec ident="myTEIlite">
<desc>This is TEI Lite with simplified heads</desc>
  <moduleRef name="teistructure"/>
  <moduleRef name="linking"/>
  <moduleRef name="core"/>
  <moduleRef name="teiheader"/>
  <elementSpec ident="head" mode="change">
    <content><rng:text/></content>
  </elementSpec>
</schemaSpec>
]]></eg>
is all that is necessary to produce a schema with the same elements
and attributes as TEI Lite, with the
slight change that the <gi>head</gi> element can contain only text.</p>

<p>As a further example, this ODD
<eg><![CDATA[
<schemaSpec ident="testrdf">
    <moduleRef url="rdfxml.rng"/>
    <moduleRef key="header"/>
    <elementSpec ident="availability" mode="change">
      <content>
	<rng:ref name="RDF"/>
      </content>
    </elementSpec>
</schemaSpec>
]]></eg>
will produce a RelaxNG schema which can be used to validate TEI conformant
headers in which the <gi>availability</gi> element may contain
metadata expressed using RDF syntax. </p>

<p>ODD documents, like any other XML source, can be transformed using
freely available TEI stylesheets or your own tools. The TEI provides a
library of suitable stylesheets for the generation of XML DTDs or
schemas and documentation, which it is hoped others will wish to
contribute to.</p>

</div>
<div><head>The next version of TEI Lite</head>

<p>It is reasonable to ask how many of these changes will affect TEI
Lite users, and what a TEI P5 compliant version of TEI Lite might look
like. This is (and will remain) an easy question to answer, since the
production of TEI Lite is used as a case study in the chapter of TEI
P5 which addresses the question of schema customization. Here are some
things that the current TEI Lite user will immediately notice when
trying to validate P4-compliant documents in a P5 regime:

<list type="ordered">
<item><gi>TEI.2</gi> is now <gi>TEI</gi> and <gi>teiCorpus.2</gi> is now <gi>teiCorpus</gi></item>
<item>all TEI elements are in the <code>http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0</code> namespace</item>
<item>many attribute values seem to  have changed… <code>Y|N</code>,
<code>yes|no</code> etc. are now uniformly
<code>true|false</code></item>
<item>some attributes have changed their names or disappeared 
<list><item>text-valued attributes have become child elements</item>
<item><code>lang</code> has become <code>xml:lang</code></item>
<item><code>id</code> has become <code>xml:id</code></item>
<item> all <code>IDREF</code> (target) values have been changed</item>
</list></item>
<item>the extended pointing  elements <gi>xptr</gi> and <gi>xref</gi> have disappeared!</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Space precludes a discussion of the rationale for each of these
changes, though none has been made lightly. For example, the removal
of text-valued attributes (the <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi>
<soCalled>janus</soCalled> elements familiar to TEI Lite users) is
partly necessitated by the observation that distinctions between
variant forms of characters must in XML be made in element content and
cannot therefore appear as attribute values. To take a familiar
example, present in the current document:
<eg><![CDATA[
a <corr resp="theobald" sic="table">babbl'd</corr>]]></eg>
becomes
<eg><![CDATA[
a <choice resp="theobald">
  <sic>table</sic>
  <corr>babbl'd</sic>
</choice>
]]></eg>
in part to support the needs of an encoder who might wish to represent
the particular glyphs used in their encoding, using the new <gi>g</gi>
element.<note place="foot">It is a pleasure to acknowledge here
that the correction of <code>gifford</code> to <code>theobald</code>
in this venerable example is due to Prof. Hans-Walter Gabler's keen
observation.</note>
</p>

<p>Both the introduction of namespaces and the changes to global
attributes <code>lang</code> and <code>id</code> are necessary
consequences of the desire for
interoperability with other XML vocabularies<note place="foot">For a
paper discussing some of the possibilities afforded by such
interoperability see 
<bibl>
Sebastian Rahtz, Norman Walsh, and Lou Burnard <title level="a">A
unified model for text markup: TEI, Docbook, and beyond</title>,
Available from <xptr
url="http://www.idealliance.org/papers/dx_xmle04/papers/03-08-01/03-08-01.html"/>.
Paper presented at XML Europe, Amsterdam, April 2004.
</bibl>
</note>. It would seem strange
indeed to retain both <ident>lang</ident> and <ident>xml:lang</ident>
when the two have identical semantics, though a case
might be made for permitting either. The changes in pointer mechanisms
though pervasive and at first sight unnecessary also represent a major
simplification. The simplicity of changing (for example)
<eg><![CDATA[
 <ptr target="SEC14"/> or <ref target="SEC14">chapter 1.4</ref>
<!-- ... -->
 <div id="SEC14"><head>Concerning identifiers</head>
<!-- ... -->
</div>]]></eg>
into
<eg><![CDATA[
 <ptr target="#SEC14"/> or <ref target="#SEC14">chapter 1.4</ref>
<!-- ... -->
 <div xml:id="SEC14"><head>Concerning identifiers</head>
<!-- ... -->
</div>]]></eg>
perhaps obscures the fact that it now becomes possible to reference
the chapter <q>Concerning identifiers</q> whether or not it is in the
same document, and whether or not an XML parser is
available to validate the reference. If the required section
were actually a part of <code>someDoc.xml</code> rather than the
same document as that containing
by the referring element, the P4 pointer above would need to be
completely modified (along with other things) as follows:
<eg><![CDATA[
 <xptr doc="someDoc" from="id(SEC14)"/>
<!-- ... -->
]]></eg>, whereas the P5 element needs to change only as follows:
<eg><![CDATA[
 <ptr target="someDoc.xml#SEC14"/>
]]></eg>

Another major difference in P5 is the replacement of the familiar
ID/IDREF mechanism, which depends on the availability of a conformant
XML parser and schema instance, with a more general link-resolution
mechanism, which need not be present for all document processing
purposes. Whether this will be regarded as a benefit or a nuisance
perhaps depends as much on general attitudes to validation as anything
else, but it is indisputably more in keeping with the way electronic
documents are currently deployed and managed on the web.</p>

</div>

<div><head>Open TEI</head>

<p>As this last point suggests, perhaps the most significant change
which the TEI is currently undergoing is its reinvention as an Open
standard. To date, all development of the TEI has been centralised and
managed by a small <soCalled>inner circle</soCalled> of researchers,
altough always with the widest possible involvement from the larger
research community. In 2004, however, the TEI consortium announced that the
Guidelines would be released under a GNU Public license, and that from
2005, all new development would take place in public on its site at
Sourceforge (<xptr url="http://tei.sf.net"/>). Feature requests and
bug tracking are already on the Sourceforge site, and the first
complete draft of P5 is scheduled to follow shortly. Experimental releases of
TEI components and tools are already available as Debian Linux
packages. However, the name <title>TEI</title> will remain a
trademark, and the direction of technical work will continue to be authorized by a TEI
Technical Council, elected by members of the Consortium. </p>


<p>The TEI thus remains a community initiative, driven primarily by
the needs of its members and users. It is hoped that moving towards an
Open Source model will encourage a more sustainable and better
devolved development process, complemented by the stability and
maintenance afforded by the structure of a <foreign>pro bono</foreign>
membership consortium. The importance of this
<foreign>rapprochment</foreign> between the TEI and the Open Source
movement should not be overlooked. </p>

<p>As we have seen, the TEI originally came into being as the result
of a perception in many different parts of the academic research
community that the rising tide of digitized media (largely known, in
those distant days, as "electronic" or even "machine-readable" texts)
threatened a war of competing formats and encoding
systems. Scholarship has always thrived on serendipity and the ability
to pass on our intellectual heritage for re-evaluation in a new
context; many at that time suspected (and events have not yet proved
them wrong) that longevity and re-usability were not high on the
priority lists of software vendors and electronic publishers. Equally,
and even before the World Wide Web, it was clear that one of the
striking virtues of converting resources into a digital form was the
consequent ability to integrate resources of different kinds and from
different places into one. At the end of the eighties there was a real
concern that the entrepreneurial forces which (then as now) drive
information technology forward would impede such integration by the
proliferation of mutually incompatible technical standards. In 2005,
the struggle between those who would apply the methods and principles
of monopoly capitalism to the business of information dissemination
and preservation and those who believe information wants to be free
shows no sign of having abated. It seems that the TEI is likely to
continue to have a major role in that struggle.</p>
<signed>Lou Burnard, European Editor TEI</signed>
<dateline>Oxford, January 2005</dateline>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
